Benjamin Luft collection of 9-11 first responders' oral histories
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
- Series 1: Oral History Interviews, April 9, 2010 through November 4, 2016
  - Philip J. Burns oral history interview conducted by Andrew Flescher, March 19, 2012, AFC 2015/048: 160
    - Moving Images
  - Gerard Ricciard oral history interview conducted by Julie Broihier, April 10, 2012, AFC 2015/048: 161
    Gerard (Jerry) is the eldest of 6 siblings. He was married in July 2001 and now has three children, including twins. He is originally from Smithtown, Long Island and then he moved to the St. James area. Jerry has worked as a special agent for the Treasury Department since 1991, working primarily on narcotics investigations and crimes against the United States. At the time of 9/11, he was working for the El Dorado Task Force as a Special Agent. His office was located at Number Four World Trade Center, one of the smaller buildings adjacent to the World Trade Center towers. Jerry was commuting from St. James every day, and each day at work was different. On the morning of 9/11, he had two new recruits that were starting. He had taken the train to work that day, but normally he would have driven to work. If he had driven, he would have parked beneath one of the towers and we probably wouldn’t have this story. Instead, he took the train to Penn Station and then got on the subway. He heard a muffled eruption and as he got off the subway people were running towards him. He heard someone say it was a car bomb but he didn’t see anything that looked like that. He could see a hole in the North Tower; paper, metal and glass were falling from the sky. He headed towards his office and started helping people as they were going down the escalator. Everyone was dirty, some bleeding. He saw one woman whose lip was hanging off so he helped her to an ambulance. He kept hearing things hitting the ground but didn’t know what it was coming from. Later he learned, it was jumpers hitting the ground or the overpass trying to escape the flames. They had no choice, either burn to death or jump. Emergency vehicles started showing up more and more and then the 2nd plane hit but he didn’t see it; he was under the South Tower. An engine that was on fire flew over his head and crashed into a nearby Burger King. A ball of fire flew in his direction and he jumped under a sanitation truck for protection. There was a lady on the other side of the truck who wanted to get out, but he told her she had to stay for safety. There was debris everywhere. He ended up grabbing her hair so she wouldn’t leave. He said he went into survival mode. He saw his four month old son Connor’s face flash before him. Jerry said he just wanted to be able to see his son again. He finally let go of the woman’s hair and doesn’t know where she went. Shortly after that he also left the safety of the sanitation truck and ended up jumping over a fence, landing on people as they were running towards a subway. He ran north and went into a tunnel and hugged a pole underground as a train was coming. Through all this, he clung to his briefcase. He got on a subway and went just a few stops before getting off. He saw jets overhead and didn’t know if they were under attack. He headed towards the Empire State Building. Cell phones were down. He got on a train leaving NY and he could see the smoke as the train was heading east. He heard people talking on the train, saying that the Pentagon had been hit as well. All his emergency equipment was in his car. His wife picked him up at the train station in Huntington and then he went to Hauppauge where his car was and headed back to the city. By that time the buildings had collapsed and he knew the goal now would be to find people. He recalls the smell, dust and dirt. It permeated everything. He headquarters was temporarily placed on the Intrepid. He would send agents out to do interviews. His other office was one of the smaller buildings in the Trade Center. Damage was done to parts of the building but not all of it. He would go there 2 or 3 times a day trying to get in and find evidence. The glass was gone on his side of the building and he could sit in his chair and look down into the giant hole. He took the flag that was on his desk and loaded his duffel bag with evidence from past cases, as well as his computer. From the promenade he would climb the piles of debris. He would go through a hole and be in the basement of his building. He would do this for weeks. He remembers EPA started showing up so he knew things were going on with the air quality. He remembers seeing Christie Todd Whitman wearing a large full face mask. He did not work on the pile or in the pit; he would safeguard criminal evidence of cases prior to 911 and now. That was his assignment. He remembers seeing George Bush speaking on the pile and he remembers that when horns blew, everyone ran for cover. He remembers sometimes sleeping on the Intrepid. When he did go home, he would leave all his clothes outside. He knows what was on them, the smell, dust, and powder. Jerry made a shadow box of some things. He remembers people lining the highways cheering; he thought that was weird. Bystanders would give out water, socks, gloves, and hard hats. The only thing he took was water because he thought that the other things were for the responders and he didn’t feel he was entitled to any of those items. He even felt guilty taking the water. He doesn’t go back to the site and doesn’t care about the memorial. He doesn’t feel like a hero. He was lucky that day. He remembers always clinging to his briefcase and feels that whatever he did was just part of his job. When he was on the train he heard one person say, "Our lives will be totally different from here on; we need to be aware and cautious." He was an agent for 10 years before 9/11 and feels his training helped him survive. He didn’t lose anyone close to him and didn’t go to any funerals…but he always clung to his briefcase.
    - Moving Images
  - Daniel J. Dooley oral history interview conducted by Dr. Benjamin Luft, April 12, 2012, AFC 2015/048: 162
    Daniel, ‘Dan’ was a retired New York City firefighter and was working as a registered nurse at Rikers Island at the time of 9/11. He was asleep that morning in his house, when his daughter called to inform him that a plane had hit one of the WTC towers. He thought it may have been a small plane, and most likely an accident. Then, the second plane hit the other tower, and soon after he got a phone call that his son, a New York City firefighter, had responded to the attacks. Dan was very worried about his son, as he watched the events unfold on T.V. and the towers collapse. He met his wife, who was playing a game of golf that morning at a local golf course. When his wife found out that their son had responded to the attacks, she broke down. Dan was able to contact his daughter-in-law, who took care of his wife, and then he decided to go down to Ground Zero to find his son. He stopped at a few local volunteer firehouses to explain his situation, and to try to get an extra “turnout” coat (firefighting gear) from them. He had difficulty obtaining the gear, but took his car anyway and drove on the LIE and over the FDR Bridge to Ground Zero. He was stopped a couple of times on the way, but was able to show his retired firefighter badge and got through the security. Dan parked his car near a firehouse by South Street Seaport about a mile away from Ground Zero, and walked towards the site. He was wearing only civilian clothing and there was dust everywhere. He went down to a couple of firehouses to find out about his son, but no one had any information about him. He was 4 or 5 blocks away, when WTC building 7 collapsed. He borrowed a cell phone from a civilian and called his wife, who told him that their son had contacted her, and that he was okay. Dan was happy and relieved that his son was alive. He went back to his car, which was covered in dust, and drove home. The next day, he found out that his friend and fellow firefighter, Frank, had perished in the attacks. He decided to help out in the rescue and recovery process and for the next 20 days, he traveled to Ground Zero by himself to assist in the rescue, recovery, and clean-up process. Dan remembers the deep camaraderie he experienced with the other workers on the pile. He particularly recalls working with Department of Transportation workers. He remembers that people were very charitable, giving out free gloves for responders. Nurses came around and offered to provide eye-washes for responders, who spent several hours on the dusty pile. Dan remembers seeing body parts, “arms and hands.” He was a firefighter for 25 years, and had seen many bodies before, so he was hardened to this experience. Dan recalls that while exploring one of the tunnels in the pile, he came across a golf ball. He used to play golf with Frank and he thought it was eerie that he should find something that reminded him of Frank in these tunnels. He later took the golf ball and buried it in a memorial that he built for Frank in his hometown. While working on the pile, Dan was wearing firefighter gear from the 1980s. He was questioned a few times because of his outdated apparel. He wanted to stay longer than the time he actually spent on the pile, but was told that the situation was under control by professional responders. After 9/11, he contacted Frank’s wife and decided to build a monument for Frank and other firefighters and civilians who perished in the towers. He managed to get donations and permission from the Town of Brookhaven and built these memorials for Frank and other fallen 9/11 firefighters in the harbor town of Port Jefferson, Long Island. Dan attended approximately 25 funerals after 9/11 in honor of fallen firefighters and police officers. He remembers that the saddest moment of his experience was watching people jumping out of the burning towers on television. Dan feels that this young generation of Americans is exceptional, especially those firefighters who went into the burning towers without hesitation to rescue people. It was terribly unfortunate that so many of them never returned home to their families. Dan also remembers the deep camaraderie he felt with other responders, and one particularly “happy” experience at Ground Zero: “I was coming out of this tunnel, and there were all these people with pails who were passing (stuff) down. I came out of the tunnel and had black soot on my face…and these people started cheering for me. I felt pretty good about that. Later on, somebody took a picture with all the black soot on my face, which I still have.”
    - Moving Images
  - Michael Diamond oral history interview conducted by Dr. Benjamin Luft, April 16, 2012, AFC 2015/048: 163
    On 9/11/2001, Michael was a NYPD officer working in the Harbor Unit based in Brooklyn. He had worked for the NYPD for 14 years. On that Tuesday morning, he was scheduled to monitor the primary elections at a school near the 69th precinct in Brooklyn. A voter at the polling booth told him that a plane had struck one of the World Trade Center buildings. He thought it was most likely a mistake, until he heard a scream and saw the TV coverage of the attack on the building. He called over his radio into the 69th precinct for a ride into his regular post at the Harbor Unit. He arrived to the post to see the smoke and flames emerging from the towers over the skyline of Manhattan. He took a police boat with five other officers and a sergeant into the North Cove Marina. On the way, the towers collapsed and when they arrived at the Marina, there were people looking to evacuate. Michael and the others started to load up the boats to bring people to safety. Michael also managed to get his brother, who worked in the area, over to Brooklyn. Michael remembered one situation where small boat broke the security zone on the East River. It turned out to be a man who was trying to find his uncle. Michael felt this man was extremely lucky he was harmed by law enforcement officers, since everyone was on heightened alert during this time. Michael ferried nearly a thousand people out of the area. He was there until about three or four in the morning. Michael also discussed his experiences responding other major disasters such as the Flight 800 disaster and the Far Rockaway crash. For him, the Far Rockaway crash was by far one of the most macabre.
    - Moving Images
  - Kevin oral history interview conducted by Dr. Benjamin Luft, April 17, 2012, AFC 2015/048: 164
    On 9/11/2001, Kevin was a recent transfer to the Emergency Management Services division within the New Jersey State Police. He had been in law enforcement for 15 years. His transfer was in effect for 9-11-2001 but he had contracted meningitis and was on leave from work. Kevin watched the events unfold on television and wanted to get back to work to assist with the NJ law enforcement response. He went back early to get clearance for work from his doctor, and on September 22, 2001 he started working at the Family Assistance Center in Liberty State Park, which was set up to provide counseling and assistance to families of WTC victims from New Jersey. New Jersey lost 746 victims to the WTC attacks. The Family Assistance Center provided various resources for family members of NJ WTC victims including mental health and grief counseling services, bereavement counseling services, FEMA aid, Small Business Administration (SBA) aid, Salvation Army and American Red Cross counselors, Department of Motor Vehicle assistance, and issuance of death certificates. The center also had a memory board for families to post pictures of their loved ones who died in the attacks. One of Kevin’s first assignments was to attend a meeting at the Family Assistance Center and make arrangements for NJ family members to visit the WTC site by boat over the NY Waterway. Over the next few months, they provided two shuttle runs per week to the WTC site. The NJ state troopers brought over nearly 100 families per trip to the WTC site. The troopers would conduct security sweeps of the boats with dogs prior to departure and checked identification of those on board. Kevin recalled that the troopers formed strong bonds with many of the family members and even with the mental health counselors who travelled with the families to assist them through the grieving process. They troopers felt good about the providing those services also knew that the family members appreciated and needed their assistance. They also learned how to prepare for reactions that families would have to seeing the WTC site, and how to guide them during a tour of the site. Many of the moments that Kevin and other NJ state troopers experienced with the families of WTC victims were outside the realm of what they were taught at the police academy. They worked long days, sometimes from 6 a.m. to 11 pm. at the Family Assistance Center without any time off. Especially considering the type of work he did at the Family Assistance Center, Kevin realized that he needed to spend time with his family and, on Halloween 2001, he asked his boss for some time off to go trick-or-treating with his daughter. Kevin also developed a bond with some of the other people he worked with, and he is still friends with many of them to this day. Kevin also mentioned the summer before 9/11; he had taken his children to the top of the WTC towers. His son was in fourth grade at the time of 9/11 and was very upset that the people who worked at the top of the towers were killed. His son later wrote a poem titled “The Internal Red Fire” about 9/11 responders, for which he was awarded a scholarship from a family member of a WTC victim. As a result of his work, Kevin formed valuable friendships with those people he worked with at the Family Assistance Center and some of the family members of WTC victims. He worked at the Family Assistance Center through March 2002, and still attends WTC victims’ family reunions each 9/11 anniversary at Liberty State Park, New Jersey.
    - Moving Images
    - Manuscripts
  - Stephen oral history interview conducted by Dr. Benjamin Luft, April 17, 2012, AFC 2015/048: 165
    Stephen worked for the Department of Emergency Management in New Jersey as part of the State Troopers office. He was off work on 9/11 for a doctor’s appointment and was on the phone when someone told him that the first plane hit. He headed to the NJ Port Authority Center to see what he could do to help. National response cellular and radio communications were cut when the 2nd plane hit. He would get information regarding coordinating certain things, but said it all seemed surreal, especially when he heard the fighter jets overhead. Stephen said that many people tried to find safe haven in New Jersey and took whatever boats they could to cross the Hudson River. He said that the adrenaline kept people going. It was a day or 2 before he had the chance to get to Ground Zero, where everything was just pulverized. There were no chairs, desks or computers, only steel beams. The smell was overwhelming. Stephen has 20 years of Emergency Medical Services training and knew he would see many people die from the health effects of the WTC disaster in the years to come. People would line the streets holding flags and cheering; others held pictures of their lost loved ones. Liberty State Park in New Jersey was set up as a Family Assistance Center. Every day Stephen would have to walk past a bulletin board that had pictures of missing people; notes that said ‘In memory of’ or ‘Have you seen this person?'. It was overwhelming. He would work 16-18 hour days at the center, and soon gained weight from the inactivity of just sitting all the time. His wife has a strong educational background in psychology, so he took her to Ground Zero so she could see the devastation and understand what he was going through. She ended up volunteering for a while. Stephen went to the Fresh Kills Landfill in Staten Island once or twice and saw the conveyors that were used to sift through the debris searching for body parts or anything that could be used to identify someone. The responders working here were looking for friends and neighbors. Part of Stephen's job was to take people on the boats from NJ to NY to see the devastation. He felt honored to help these people and felt it was his duty. Initially, he was assigned to the emergency management area and then in mid-October he went to work in the Governor’s office, helping to set up programs and resources that were badly needed to help families. Stephen said that geographically and chronologically, the further away people were from the WTC disaster, the more he noticed that they would forget or did not care about the tragedy. After 2 or 3 years, people who lived in Battery Park City did not want tourists visiting and looking around. They were done with disaster and wanted to move on. Stephen said that we were a complacent country before 9/11, but not anymore. He said that while many died on that day, an amazing number of people lived and were saved by first responders. He hopes our society allows this event to be taught in schools as part of history, so that children will learn and remember about that day. Stephen says there are no guarantees in life and no promises for a future. If not for his wife, he would have had a nervous breakdown. He said this was the darkest time of his life and he expressed gratitude to his wife for helping him through this time, and understanding what he was going through. Now when they talk about taking a trip, they do it. They make plans and follow through. They do not take anything for granted.
    - Moving Images
    - Manuscripts
  - James oral history interview conducted by Dr. Benjamin Luft, April 24, 2012, AFC 2015/048: 166
    James was working a job at a school in Islip doing ironwork on 9/11. His boss came and told him that planes had flown into the towers and James thought, "How horrible," and immediately became emotional. He felt the need to go; his dad was an iron worker as well, so the profession was in his blood. James said that for some unknown reason prior to 9/11, he had begun taking supplies and equipment from the company he was working for. It was just small amounts, but enough to start a decent stockpile. He took torches and oxygen and other cutting equipment. He didn’t know why he was taking it; he said he just knew he had to. So when James heard of the disaster, he decided on his own to go to Ground Zero. He called his good friend, Lance, to go with him. He felt this was his opportunity to do something good, something he could be proud of. For once in his life he had something to offer so he loaded up his Dodge Ram and headed down the expressway. He felt that everything that happened was for a reason--this was something he learned while in AA. He ended up around the Jacob Javits center and followed a bus into Ground Zero. The scene was like the movie "Planet of the Apes"--everything was covered in a snowy dust. He and Lance fudged their way around a restricted area and ended up on an empty street. He went to work by the American Express building, cutting and burning steel using the tools he had taken from his job. He felt guilty about that, but said that he realized that this was the reason he took those tools from work. James says he has his demons but at that moment when he was working at Ground Zero, for the first time in his life he felt "110%." He felt completely focused for the first time in his life, and this had never happened to him before or after 9/11. At one point, while working by the pile, James went through a walkway that had collapsed and he saw the leg of a fireman sticking up. Firemen would put a glow stick in an area, and then the iron workers would go in and dig. James had hoped to find some survivors-- but he never did. James spoke about a letter he received from a fourth grade student that was in a box of cookies sent to thank the WTC responders. He said that made him feel so good and so appreciated. He remembers walking around St. Mark’s Church, and passed a restaurant where the tables were set. It was as if the place were frozen in time but covered in dust. The cars in the parking lot were covered with dust and debris. James said that he just walked around and found places to work. Fires would spontaneously erupt; it was scary. James doesn’t even like to watch TV anymore. He doesn’t like scenes where cars are racing down the road. It brings back very bad memories. The enormity and finality of all, the insanity, he doesn’t have the words to describe how he felt. Someone had said to him “(It) smells like death kid, worse than Vietnam”. James said that he felt bad because he felt good about working at Ground Zero. He felt guilty that this was the first time in his life that he felt “110%.” James felt like he was part of a family-- a brotherhood. He worked 14-18 hour days for about 2 weeks. He wore no face mask or protective equipment while working Ground Zero. After a while, when he realized that he was not going to find any survivors, it became more like a business and like a regular job, and then he didn’t feel any satisfaction from the work. So then he left and got a job with a union as an ironworker. James spoke about how the ironworkers write the floor number in soapstone on the front of the beams when a building is being built. When he was at Ground Zero, he saw some of these numbers on the fallen beams. In 2003, James had a fall on a work site and was badly injured. He has had over 14 surgeries since that time and has been mostly on disability. He is 41 years old and said “life is just a bag of minutes”. He is grateful that righteousness prevailed. His faith became stronger and he feels closer to God. He told us that he felt it was God that was asking him to take that equipment, because he would need it to help when he went to dig at Ground Zero. He said there are no coincidences in life. There is no place he would rather have been at the time.